[SPEAKER_00]: Says Bhante, since childhood, I've been trapped in self-hatred, seeing only ugliness, failure and burden in my reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: People say that I'm too harsh on myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know it's true, yet the cycle persists.
[SPEAKER_00]: I shun mirrors even, fear new beginnings and hide myself, convinced I will never be good enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: How does one escape such a prison of self-hatred?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well,
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, whether it's the self-hatred or self-indulgence, it stems from the mind that's untamed and has had it its own way for too long.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever intents
[SPEAKER_01]: Moods or emotions you're going through, the intensity of those things comes from the wildness of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like everybody has times or periods or... moods of self-hatred or, as I said, self-aggrandizing, whatever is the opposite of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then they usually, you know, will not necessarily dwell on those things as long as some other people might, for whatever circumstantial reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to recognize that the problem is not really whether you have thoughts of self-hatred or thoughts that you're the greatest person in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that the intensity of those thoughts reveals the degree of your mind, how much it's not actually tamed, how much it disregards you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the real problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, self-loathing, self-hatred is not something that you've
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's a symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're reaching the point of, like, chronic, what that person seems to describe, like, chronic self-loathing, it means, like, chronic untameness of its mind, that just keeps picking that for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's irrelevant, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it like this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in some other way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it weren't that way, it would have been some other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that lack of tameness, that wilderness of that mind, will find its ways of expressing itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The degree of how wild it is, how little regard it has for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the training of purification is the training of that animal and that in itself would then reduce the intensity of whatever that animal chooses to engage with, whatever the habits are, whether it's self-loathing or this or that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes from the same place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That the mind desires things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the mind desires things and if that desire has been kept, has been allowed,
[SPEAKER_01]: To persist and proliferate unchecked, it will become pathological, in a way, the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will reach the extremes, that it's now just unbearable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the only reason is, that is such, is because the mind has been allowed to sort of
[SPEAKER_01]: Walk those pathways repeatedly, over and over and over again, and further and further and further, and now it's just like a smooth canal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just flies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind just slides through it, straight at the end point, where it left off.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that needs to be undone.
[SPEAKER_01]: That needs to be prevented from proliferating, from getting worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Needs to be tamed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the mind will... it's going to resist it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's gonna resist.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why even if people did not have self-loathing to begin with, when they start keeping the precepts and trying to tame the animal and maybe, you know, put a lid on their desires, they're gonna start self-loathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind will then turn against itself, against you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's literally like the wild dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to have a wild dog next to you and
[SPEAKER_01]: Constantly you're throwing raw meat to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just because it sees all what it wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're giving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The moment you stop, it starts to growl at you or whoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It gets agitated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let alone if you now keep it hungry for a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that is the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the entire gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: The laying down the foundations of virtue, precepts, sense restraint, to basically contain that animal when it starts to self-loathe,
[SPEAKER_01]: For right reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the reasons of depriving it of those depraved ways, desires and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's difficult not to...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're self-loathing and then you've...
[SPEAKER_00]: I shouldn't be doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same, like, as we spoke about, like, with anxiety, like, oh, I shouldn't be feeling this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, it's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a symptom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, self-loathing, yeah, you shouldn't... you shouldn't be like... you shouldn't allow yourself the images associated with it to... to like wallow in it and make it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you need to recognize... you also need to teach yourself to stop regarding that as a problem and start seeing it as a symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a symptom of the untamed mind that when I'm not self-loathing, I am enabling in its untamed ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, sure, you can be... you can leave your mind untamed, you can allow its desires, you could think it's not a problem, self-loathing can come up, and then I can tell you, well, just calm down...
[SPEAKER_01]: Embrace it, be, you know, accept, don't resist it, calm down in the body, feel the sensations, watch your nostrils, concentrate, forget about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's, yeah, it feels like, oh, it went away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wow, it helped me.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, ask yourself, if I tell you to do that and you do that, what are the chances of it coming back?
[SPEAKER_01]: A hundred percent.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already know the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a hundred percent it's going to come back.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then do it again, what I told you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And do you think now these chances have been reduced?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might like to think they'll be reduced.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can do it for ten years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever it comes, you do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to keep coming back.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you already know that even from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, believing that it will somehow magically resolve itself through your calming techniques and learning how to be calm amidst these things, it's like you already know that it doesn't work that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already know that it's just like wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it gets too much, whatever, calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Calm yourself, whichever way you've been calming yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's... completely has nothing to do with uprooting it or practicing rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you need to calm yourself up is because you still...
[SPEAKER_01]: Calm yourself down is because you still take up the symptom as a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you're still not seeing where the real problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you're just pasting.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just comes up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Comes up, put down.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why is it coming up?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's coming up because the mind does not respect you, does not listen to you, and it leads you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are not leading it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is no magical recipe for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will just help you through mere coping, when things get too much, and then just magically they resolve themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, you go into like a self-hypnosis, sorry, I mean meditation,
[SPEAKER_01]: Every now and then, feel pleasant, watch sensations, and then, that just, just, miraculously, yeah, yeah, yeah, is just making this mind less wild, less, sort of, disrespectful towards me, less self-loathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you make a determination to constantly stay on the level of calming whatever comes up, again, you are still managing the symptoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you have such thoughts... And, by the way, the same, even if, as I said, even if it's not the extreme... extremely proliferated cases of self-loathing or conceit or...
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of the five hindrances is already that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of the... of centrality is already that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of ill-will, it's already the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the thoughts that come up with it, you need to recognize the symptom of a problem of an untamed mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mind were tamed, these things wouldn't come up in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would already be calm amidst the disturbances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so I've got to tame my mind, not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, do you really want... And, see, well, that's the irony of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even people that practice the calming as coping...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's, yeah... Well, they do it because they, underneath it, as I said, they believe that it will lead to a substantial calming of the more fundamental kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, just ask yourself, how many times you've been doing it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And, if you were honest,
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there any degree... Like, you might say, oh, things don't come up as much as before, but that's because maybe you change your environment, maybe your coping became more... your management coping became more quicker, because you've been doing it for so long.
[SPEAKER_01]: But fundamentally, just if you boil it all down and ask yourself, yeah, but can it still arise in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there...
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there nothing that I could sort of put in between, so that these thoughts, these states of mind, can't even come up?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the answer is no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't even know where to apply that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't even know where to begin, because you've been practicing at the wrong place, in the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the place, the thing to put in between, what is the thing that you could put in between there, so that it doesn't come up again?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, you already know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your decisions?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your decisions, your non-action towards the unbeneficial things, your sense restraint, your virtue, is already what you're putting in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it's not going to remove the persisting
[SPEAKER_01]: You're besetting unpleasant symptoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're treating the infection with the antibiotics.
[SPEAKER_01]: The wound still hurts, still itches, but it's being treated from the inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you stick to the regime and follow the right diet and not aggravate it to scratching or putting random crap on top of it that's actually making it worse,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will heal up and then you will not have a need to learn how to scratch skillfully and manage and do this or that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are addressing the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, somebody might ask, well, can I do both?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I be addressing the mind and coping and doing meditation techniques and calming?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you have to ask yourself, well, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I'm addressing the mind rightly, that should already be calming.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I need to address the mind and continue my calming techniques, I'm not addressing the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's addressing things in the roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're pulling the roots, you don't need to be constantly trimming the ever-growing branches.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you think you can or you should be doing both, it's because you're not actually pulling out the roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when things get too much, as I said, you're already going to be giving in to the management, even without making a conscious, misguided practice out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are already coping.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not giving in, you are already coping.
[SPEAKER_01]: By practicing restraint, you're already coping.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're kind of coping in a less wrong way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where restraint in itself, it's not going to free you from it, but it certainly
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to make it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's certainly going to keep you aligned with where the roots are, where the mind is, where the taming is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I said in the previous talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start doing that restraint rightly, you don't perpetuate your wrong views of management and valuing the release from the symptoms as the release from the root problem, because that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to fall into that view.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you keep giving in to management of the symptoms out of the pressure of the problem,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you still believe that abating of the symptoms, to that extent, the problem is solved.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, the only reason you can know the problem is because of the symptoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to use the recognition and discernment of the symptoms to keep an eye on the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if you start practicing like that, even that sense restraint, which is through means of coping, actually, that's what I mean, like what I said in the previous talk, that becomes purification now.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which was just mere saying no to this, saying no to that, saying no to things that I learned are unbeneficial, well, now that's sort of coming down to where it should be.
[SPEAKER_01]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: where the mental training is, so you're not afraid of thoughts that come up and try to manage them or calm them because it's too unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize, yeah, that's a symptom, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It builds up, comes to my face, trying to make me act.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all because of the untamed mind underneath it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, by not acting out of this, the mind is getting the message that the pressure it throws at me to act is working less and less and less.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that calms the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, screaming child, whenever it screams, you give it what it wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are conveying a message that screaming works.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look, I influence this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't get it myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need you to get it for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I scream and threaten and whatever else, and you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you encourage that behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now that it works, each time it comes up, you practice not hearing of my screams.
[SPEAKER_01]: You practice thinking the opposite thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll wait for that, and I'll still continue until you give me what I want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's usually... well, not usually, that's always how this ends.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you finish your calming, you go back to things that the mind wanted from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like, no, I won't be denying, I won't be replacing the thoughts, the screams of a child.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll stay with it, so that it sees that I see it, and I'm not giving in to its demands.
[SPEAKER_01]: By body, by speech, by mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not allowing these thoughts in a sense of... not I'm trying to get rid of them, but in a sense of I'm not allowing them to take the center stage, take place of my activation, of my welcome in accepting them, thinking, trying to resolve them, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't be engaged with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but take it up, take it up, solve it, solve the doubt, solve the pressure, solve the sensuality, solve the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pressure to solve means taking up at a face value of what the mind's trying to make me
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure towards, act towards.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by not managing it, by staying with the mind on that level, it sees that you see it, and it sees that you're not doing what it wants you to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: What then option, what other option will then the child have?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to tire itself out, and it's going to sit down quietly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it might even ask you nicely.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, yeah, and you might have to go through that
[SPEAKER_01]: Many times, because many times before, you would have allowed such behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, after a while, it realizes that this is better.
[SPEAKER_01]: It factually realizes, hold on, actually, it's... it doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: This upset, kicking, screaming, threatening, just brings me more, more bother, more disturbance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I know it won't let me go in that direction, so I might as well not even bother trying.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, there will be no symptoms for you to manage.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the right aiming.
[SPEAKER_01]: The right aiming, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the right endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the right endurance, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the whole point of those thoughts, and accepting them at the face value, as the problem, and trying to deal with them, or counter them, is the mind is hidden behind them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're trying to address them, shape them,
[SPEAKER_01]: Manipulate them, change them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you need to take them up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by taking them up, you don't see the... you stop seeing the screaming child.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you're concerned about is what it does to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must stop this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must counter that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that, all of that smokescreen, thoughts, ah, ah, ah, ah, is to just make me give in to the fact that the child is untamed and I'm enabling it.